hello and welcome it's November 11th
2024 we're in active inference guest
stream number 92.1 with Max eer we're
going to be discussing a variety of
thermodynamic and basian topics it
should be very exciting if you're
watching live feel free to write any
questions in the live chat Max will go
through some sections of several papers
and I will read questions and ask
questions so thank you Max for joining
looking forward to hearing about this
take it away great um yeah thank you uh
for the introduction and thanks for
having me on uh really excited to talk
about this stuff um so there are a few
papers I want to talk about um one
called thermodynamic linear algebra
about kind of a novel Hardware approach
to solving linear algebra problems and
another one called thermodynamic based
inference which is similar similarly
about using these these new
thermodynamic Hardware devices for beas
and inference problems um and but before
I get into that I just wanted to make a
note on kind of like the story of this
work and how it evolved because I think
it's pretty interesting um so I'm
working at a company a startup called um
normal Computing and where we started
off was just thinking about what's kind
of the best hardware Paradigm for for AI
and especially probalistic machine
learning uh because these these are some
of the most challenging tasks
computationally and seen as some of the
most necessary to be able to do kind of
robust um AI without you know
hallucinations and a big approach to
that is is probalistic machine learning
um and a lot of our approach was was
inspired by this report that came out of
of um a workshop in 2019 called
thermodynamic Computing um and I'm
sharing it uh can you see my my screen
here what I'm sharing okay yeah so there
there's this one quote here in the
introduction that I think really
summarized the point it says somewhat
paradoxically while avoiding
stochasticity in Hardware we are
generating it in software for various
machine learning techniques at
substantial computational and energetic
cost uh so one of the big kind of
takeaways from the work they did in this
um this Workshop was there was kind of a
consensus that emerged that we're
working so hard to suppress the
randomness that comes up naturally in
our hardware and then we need Randomness
actually
to run you know various randomized
algorithms especially in prob wisom
machine learning and so if there were
some way to just use the randomness
that's naturally there that we know
about due to thermodynamics to achieve
those algorithmic goals maybe we would
save a lot of energy basically so that
was kind of one of the the Inspire one
of the ideas we were inspired by um but
the first you know step along this
journey was uh so there was an earlier
paper um where we basically proposed
circuit that are capable of sampling
from a normal distribution um and I'll
get more into the math of why that
happens you know why do circuits that
look like this allow you to sample from
a multivariate gaussian um but so this
was kind of the first work that was
published at normal actually before I
started working there called
thermodynamic AI in the fluctuation
Frontier but how you can think of this
is this is the electronic analog of a
system of coupled harmonic oscillators
so if you can just think about a bunch
of masses that are coupled together by
Springs and um that are also damped so
they they have friction um acting on
them and there's also noise acting on
them so kind of damped damped system of
harmonic oscillators uh driven by noise
that's the kind of system that we're
talking about in in these works and
we're just kind of looking at this
electronic analog which is completely uh
analogous completely isomorphic to that
that picture in terms of masses on
Springs um so one of the first problems
we interested in solving was solving a
linear system of equations so you can
think of this as if I have a few planes
in N dimensional space here I have three
planes in a three-dimensional space um
and in general I I have n planes in an N
dimensional space and I want to find the
one point where they all intersect
assuming that there there is such a
point um and you can think of that
mathematically as I'm giving a matrix a
and a vector B um and I want to find the
point x that satisfies this equation um
ax equals B uh so solving this kind of
problem has has tons of applications in
economics you know engineering but also
in in AI for for you know training um
neural networks more efficiently um you
know if you can solve linear systems
quickly then there's benefits to
training Etc um so that's one of the
first problems that we decide to to look
at and well so I think that it's
interesting to compare our approach with
earlier approaches to um analog
Computing basically because this is
something that people have actually
tried to do for for quite a while is
build analog computers in other words
where this the signals are not stored as
binary numbers ones and zeros but can
take values in between and so you're
kind of using the capacity of the
hardware to represent more precise
numbers um than just a one and a zero
and in theory that seems to make sense
uh but the big problem that analog
Computing ran into is is basically that
there's a lot of noise that's present
and noise and imprecision kind of
prevents you from answering from solving
these problems like like linear systems
of equations uh with the accuracy that
you that is needed uh by the application
um so I guess the the big Insight of of
this work in this thermodynamic linear
algebra paper is that if you model the
noise if you understand the noise in
your system well enough and you model
that noise then you can actually predict
the behavior of the system on the
distribution level level even if the
system is UN unpredictable on the TR
trajectory level um and the way we
describe that modeling the noise is
using what's called a stochastic
differential equation so here uh
equation two here I've written is a
stochastic differential equation where
I'm saying that DX the change in the
state of the system which is really a
collection of voltages on capacitors in
the circuit uh the way it changes in
time has two components the first is
this term which you can think which is
called the drift term and you can think
of that as kind of the predictable part
of the change in the state and it's the
gradient of this quadratic function um
and then the second term is the noise
term so that's the result of kind of the
random forces from the environment um
and what this actual potential energy
function here corresponds to is exactly
that system of coupled masses on Springs
or harmonic oscillators um which we've
kind of drawn uh here Illustrated in a
way that like you can basically think of
the system as being a bunch of little
little balls coupled together by Springs
that are all being jostled around um by
noise um and so the problem we wanted to
solve right is that we had this Matrix a
and a vector B and we wanted to find the
point x such that ax equals B right and
the way we're going to do that using
this this physical system is by allowing
it to come to equilibrium meaning that
after it's kind of run for enough time
under under these Dynamics eventually
the state will be uncertain but the
state will be described by a probability
distribution that is the you know the
boltman distribution the exponential of
the negative potential energy uh and so
because the potential energy here is a
is a quadratic function the um the
distribution of this form where you have
e to the minus V ofx where V ofx is this
quadratic is just a gaussian and it
turns out that the mean of that Gan is a
a inverse B which is exactly the
solution to that system of linear
equations um and the co variance Matrix
is actually a inverse so there's there's
I guess two things to notice here the
first is that if we want the mean of the
linear system of if we want the answer
to the linear system of equations we can
just allow this system of coupled
harmonic oscillators to come to
equilibrium and then estimate the mean
of its state and if we actually if we
wanted something else if we wanted the
um inverse of the Matrix a then what we
could do is we could allow the system to
come to equilibrium and then estimate
all of the second moments of its state
or in other words estimate its
covariance Matrix which turns out to be
this a inverse here um so I also I want
to expand a little bit on this idea of
like what do I mean when I say that we
can model the system and we can predict
Its Behavior at the distribution level
even though it's unpredictable at the
trajectory level right so when I wrote
that when I showed that equation this
equation two on on the earlier slide
what I mean by when when I say it's
unpredictable at the the trajectory
level is that if I know X of T I can't
predict like X of t+ one with certainty
right because there's this noise that
acts as a force on on the state and so
you would need to you know the what
those the values of those random numbers
are going to determine what the state is
at time t plus one um but if I know like
initially if I have some probability
distribution for the state at time T1
and I want to know what's the
probability distribution of the state of
time T2 that is a question I can answer
using this equation um and just for an
illustration of this on the left hand
side here this kind of blue um twisting
path is a trajectory of the system where
I've initialized it at at this point
over here and then I've run it for a
long amount of time and the state of the
system here there's only two variables
X1 and X2 kind of orbits around in this
in this ellipse um but if I instead of
just running one of these simulations
running this one uh trajectory if I ran
many of these simulations and sampled
the initial state from kind of a from a
normal distribution centered on this
point and then I look at the
distribution over time for that
collection of you know many thousands of
trajectories I would get this plot here
on the right and so what you see that
the big there's a big difference between
these two pictures in that the left one
we have this trajectory which is
behaving in kind of an unpredictable and
random way but the distribution itself
is behaving in a in a very predictable
and in nice kind of smooth way um and
and one another way to think about this
is that the equation I showed earlier is
a stochastic differential equation
called a lement equation and it
describes the Dynamics in terms of the
left picture in terms of the trajectory
or at the trajectory level but if I want
an equation that describes what is
happening in the right picture um that
would be the fuer plon equation which
describes the Dynamics at the
distribution level and so it's it's
basically it's nice to be able to have
these two pictures in mind at the same
time on the one hand we're thinking
about the trajectory level and on the
other hand we're thinking about the the
distribution level picture of the
Dynamics um and so when we go up to to
higher Dimensions it's not as easy to
make you know to make this plot I can't
make uh I have no way to easily draw you
know a 10-dimensional hyper ellipsoid
the way I can do it in two Dimensions
but there is still a way we can
visualize it and the way we can
visualize it is by looking at the
covariance matrices um so I guess just
to go back here like what really are
these ellipses well these ellipses
really each of these ellipses really
represents a whole distribution a normal
distribution um and this ellipse is kind
of the typical place where you would
expect to find points that are drawn
from that distribution um but another
way of describing the the properties of
that distribution is by its covariance
Matrix which describes all of the kind
of paraly par wise correlations between
all the different variables for here we
only have two variables so it would be 2
by two but if if we had 10 variables it
would be 10 by1 here we we have it for
you know eight eight variables so it's 8
by8 um and what we're looking at here is
really um over time as we go from kind
of this black circle on the left side to
this red ellipse on the right side you
can think of that process in higher
dimensional in higher dimensions in this
eight dimensional case as how this
Matrix here is changing over time so
it's kind of the same the same thing but
now we're just watching a video of how
the coari Matrix changes over time
instead of plotting many ellipses uh at
different moments in time uh now another
interesting thing about this video here
is that this isn't a simulation um this
is actually experimental uh
demonstration that we we did on the
hardware that we we created at normal
Computing um this on circuits that look
essentially like this uh so these are
just electron as I mentioned earlier
these are just electronic
implementations or realizations of kind
of coupled harmonic oscillator
that happen to come to this equilibrium
state which is a multivariate normal
distribution and which has these
properties that you can use it to solve
linear systems of equations and and get
the inverse of Matrix um I guess yeah
just one more word of detail here so so
this input Matrix here is the Matrix a
and then Target inverse this is the
actual inverse of a that you can do just
you know numerically you can compute the
inverse um and then what these hopefully
and in fact do kind of arrive to are are
the are estimates close estimates of the
inverse of the Matrix a um because
that's the covariance Matrix is supposed
to be proportional to the inverse um so
you may be wondering at this point uh
you know this this seems interesting but
but why is it that we would go to all
this effort to actually try to solve
linear systems and or invert matrices in
a completely new way right um what about
this approach is promising so um one
thing that's promising about it is that
we have kind of theoretical results that
show that we get better ASM totic
scaling um as the problem size increases
with this um thermodynamic architecture
than the state-of-the-art digital
algorithms do to solve the same problem
um so without uh yeah I can talk more
about like the difference between the
overdamped and the underdamped at some
point but just the the headline here if
we look at this one row linear system
what this is saying is that basically on
the digital state-of-the-art methods
take like order of D Squared you know
the the the amount of time scales with a
square of Dimension to solve a linear
system using something like the
conjugate gradient method for example um
whereas with our kind of thermodynamic
approach you get an amount of time um
scaling with with d so like order order
of n instead of order of N squared so
you have some kind of like polinomial
speed up there um and we proposed a
number of like other algorithms in that
paper too so the one for inverting a
matrix um I I basically explained how
that one works it's just you you end up
estimating like the second moments
instead of estimating the mean of the
state um and there you also get like a
polinomial Advantage because instead of
taking like order of n cubed you get
order of N squared um and we also have
algorithms for getting the determinant
of a matrix or solving something uh
called the yov equation which is a
matrix you know Matrix equation that
kind of generalizes the idea of the
inverse um so one other thing I wanted
to show actually is just kind of an
animation or like maybe a more Vivid
illustration of what's going on here so
if we this this uh what you're seeing
here is just like a simulation of a
two-dimensional coupled harmonic
oscillator system um where right now the
Matrix a is just the identity Matrix and
uh so in other words there's no coupling
between the two harmonic oscillators we
have two separate harmonic oscillators
that aren't coupled together and the
coordinate of one is plotted as the x
axis and the coordinate of the other is
plotted as the y- axis um so because
they're not coupled we wouldn't expect
see any correlation between them and and
we don't in fact um and there's also
noise being added um so I can kind of
change the amount of noise here by
increasing the temperature um and I can
change you know the resistance to change
the amount of damping um and and change
the inductance which is essentially like
changing the mass of of the the Mass on
a spring and by kind of tuning these
parameters I can get something that
looks more or less like I'm getting a
bunch of samples from this multivariate
normal distribution um and in fact I am
and I can look here at the marginals and
see these are samples from these you
know these are the histogram basically
looks like a normal distribution um
although just because all the samples
seem to be to have the right
distribution that doesn't mean that the
samples are independent from each other
they could all be you know highly
correlated and so we can also look at
kind of autocorrelation function here
where basically the you know the more
you crank up the noise the faster the
correlation decays in other words it's
if you want to predict where will the
next sample be based on the current
sample if there's very little noise
that's kind of easy to do but if if
there's a lot of noise that's really
hard to do um and I can also just take
samples less frequently if I don't want
as much correlation so that's what I'm
doing here is I'm kind of cranking up
the amount of the interval between
samples and now that will you know
suppress correlation between samples uh
a bit um but at this point this is
there's something a little bit trivial
about this example because they're just
two harmonic oscillators that aren't
coupled to each other at all so really
what we're interested in is is when we
couple them together um so I think yeah
we would change this kind of term and so
what this ellipse now is the ellipse has
changed and it's predicting you know
where we expect to see the samples now
that there's a coupling between these
these two masses on Springs um and I
think it's nice just to think
intuitively about why does it happen why
do we expect to see the distribution
look like this when we turn on a
coupling between the Springs well it's
basically just that like we instead of
having two separate masses on Springs
that are oscillating by themselves now
there's another spring that's pulling
them together and so they want to be
close together right and so that means
that we're we're likely to see points
where the position of X1 is similar to
the position of X2 whether they're both
positive or both negative and that's
kind of exactly what we're seeing um as
as we see samples is kind of filling in
this this ellipse um so yeah I just
wanted to show that kind of Animation
that's a this is just a kind of uh some
JavaScript code I wrote a while ago as
kind of a visualization tool for that
um and I also yeah I have the paper
pulled up here and I can talk more about
like how how do we um there are a few
things I could talk more about so for
example like how do we derive these
complexity results of the ASM totic
scaling or how do these other algorithms
work like um the determine estimation um
but yeah I want to maybe at this point
pause and see if if there were any
questions either from the audience or
Daniel or anything
yeah awesome okay anyone can write
questions in the uh chat yeah hearing
more though about how do
you pull out different analytically
useful values
[Music]
from heat and what does that mean I it
taking a stab at it now but revisiting
it I mean how is it that there are these
tractable useful quantities arising out
of physical objects like
this right yeah I think that's a good
question um I mean to to go back to kind
of yeah the history of like so first of
off like the first thing people tried to
do was just pure analog Computing where
they didn't really consider you know the
noise or assumed you could suppress the
noise enough and that analog Computing
approach is based on a system that
physically solves a differential
equation uh so whereas our approach is a
system that physically solves a
stochastic differential equation but you
can still it's still useful to think
about the analog case where there's no
noise and where you're just trying to
solve a differential equation um because
uh you know one thing you might think to
do is if you want to solve a
differential equation instead of just
solving it numerically on a computer you
could actually just try to build a
system that actually evolves according
to the differential equation you want
right so that's like one perspective on
why do these physical objects do useful
computations because it's kind of like
saying we're going to build the physical
system that behaves in that way instead
of trying to simulate it um and I guess
yeah another perspective is that well so
with the with the linear systems right
like you can in theory you can solve
linear systems on an analog Computing
device as well that doesn't have any
noise and what's kind of going on there
is that the um you're basically doing
very uh efficient multiply and
accumulate operations in a sense in that
if you want to add together like N
Things um digitally that's going to
basically take order of end steps um but
if if you want to add together end
things kind of using some analog device
there are ways to do it that are more
more like constant time so for example
if I have n wires that all converge at
one point and send a current into each
one of those n wires then the current
that comes out is the sum of those
currents so it's kind of a way of doing
of like adding together all of those
nend things in constant time so I think
those two perspectives are kind of
useful that one we get very efficient
analog multiply and accumulate
operations and the other is that um
we're kind of building the system
instead of simulating it in some
sense what is the
transferability of these shapes like do
you have it work really well on this 5x5
Matrix but then you need to go back to
square zero for 6x6 or how do you deal
with making on the Fly changes or
adapting to specific
problems right yeah so that's a very
good question right like how you know
how does it how do these things work in
particular when we go up to like the
limit of like much larger matrices which
is relevant for you know the big kind of
AI and Industrial applications what what
we what we found is is that generally
these algorithms behave um pretty well
as we increase Dimension over a large
range of different dimensions we can go
up to thousands of dimensions and still
get the answer very accurately um but
there are other properties of the Matrix
that are relevant too that can make it
hard to solve the problem uh one that's
very important for example is the
condition number of the Matrix um so if
you think about those ellipses uh well I
guess I can just go yeah scroll down
here if for a matrix well the condition
number is the ratio of like the largest
singular value to the smallest singular
value of a matrix and what the singular
values are is they're the length of like
this kind of this long axis here and
this short axis here uh and so an
ellipse that's very long and skinny has
a very large condition number basically
the condition number basically describes
how long and skinny the the ellipse is
or if it's in high Dimensions it's like
some kind of n dimensional pancake if it
has an N if it has a large condition
number and basically
yeah um matrices with harder with larger
condition numbers end up being harder to
invert or to solve a linear system for
if the Matrix a has a large condition
number um but you know there's still uh
there's still ways to do it but it's
that's I would say one of the bigger
challenges to generalization is that
like as you go up to higher Dimensions
it's kind of easier to get matrices that
end up having very large condition
numbers so more can go wrong I
guess and you you to what extent rely on
repeated um
decorrelated long-term sampling of
single objects versus
parallelized or replicated sampling
across objects and then what is that
have to do with
ergodicity yeah so um I think I'll first
answer the question about ergodicity
actually because um yeah I think that
that's a that's a very good question
that's that's a very good way to phrase
the question actually um because if I
look at this plot on the left I this is
just a single trajectory right that I've
run for a very long amount of time and
it turns out that if I just take enough
samples of this single trajectory um
that even if even if those samples are
kind of correlated with each other um it
still you know will work but if if if I
have n samples it's better to have n
uncorrelated samples and end correlated
samples but I don't need to actually run
many trajectories in parallel I can just
run one and it turns out that that one
trajectory has the same statistics the
same mean and covariance as if I had run
a th you know or a thousand or a million
separate trajectories and that doesn't
happen for every you know for every
stochastic differential equation but it
does happen for this one and that
property is called ergodicity right the
property of ergodicity is that the
Ensemble averages and the time averages
you know are the same they have the same
statistics um so on the right hand side
here this is kind of looking at The
Ensemble picture which would be more
like if I had used parallelization and
and built many of the devices and kind
of random in parallel um so I guess the
answer the question of like which one do
we do or which one you know in practice
is more useful you can do either one um
I think that it's it's a it's kind of a
knob or a lever you have to turn if you
if you have more if you can pay more for
more Hardware uh and you can pay more
energy then you can solve the problem
Faster by running many trajectories in
parallel whereas if you only want you
know one device that that only runs one
of these trajectories you can just take
samples at different points in time and
because of ergodicity it's the same as
The Ensemble statistics
basically cool carry on cool okay yeah I
thought those were all all great
questions so thanks um yeah I guess
there was one other thing I wanted to
say just at a kind of a high level about
like how do we go about getting these
complexity results um because you can
imagine there might be something subtle
about it just because this algorithm for
example is never actually guaranteed to
give you the right answer because it's
based on Randomness uh you know the
state is not gu the mean is not
guaranteed to converge to the you know
to the solution to the linear system
it's just very likely to do that um and
so you need basically I think of it as
it's um yeah it's was this term that was
coined by uh
I forget his name a computer scientist
um Leslie I think or what was his name
yeah I forget his name but
um it's it's called probably
approximately correct um is the idea
that you have a computation that with a
high probability will be within a
certain radius you know a within a
certain error tolerance of the correct
solution and so that's kind of the
approach we take to quantifying like the
runtime and analysis for these
algorithms um and I guess an example of
that is down here in the appendix um
where you can kind of find we have
bounds on um let's see where is
this yeah it will be down
here right
um yeah so we basically have a bound on
how long do you need the time to be in
order to have the state close small
closer than Epsilon to the solution with
probably with probability at least P
basically and so all of our results are
formulated in that framework of you
choose the success probability you
choose the relative error tolerance and
then you get out a time basically that
you need to run your system for you need
to average for um and those kind of
results are quoted up here in these uh
these tables basically um but yeah so I
think that's really what I had to say on
the on the thermol linear asra paper
unless there are any other questions
about that and I think otherwise I'll
move on to talking about this um
thermodynamic Asian inference paper I
guess let let me ask one question about
that last bound uhhuh um how do you get
there did you build different objects
and then back cast the formal
relationships or do you play around with
the formalisms and then ask if or how a
physical object could realize
it right so yeah so all these
mathematical results are derived within
a pretty abstract framework um which is
the abstract framework is just the
stochastic differential equation so in
other words in order to derive these
complexity results we just start by
assuming that the the system evolves
according to the stochastic differential
equation and once we've made that
assumption we can completely forget
about the physical implementation
whether it's actual masses on Springs or
capacitors and inductors or whatever
those details become irrelevant and so
we're just talking about the kind of
mathematical properties of how quickly
the distribution converges under these
Dynamics to the stationary distribution
of this equation
basically okay cool um so yeah so one
thing that we noticed basically when we
were doing that that when we were
writing that thermol linear paper is
that we noticed that while we'd gotten
these very nice and satisfying um
polinomial speedups that we predicted it
seemed like we could some we somehow
should be able to get even better
speedups and the reason for that was
that much of the runtime of running
those Thermo and your algebra algorithms
was actually dominated by just taking
averages of the state of the system um
in other words if we go back to this
picture
um here it turned out that we start we
initialize the system out of equilibrium
it it very rapidly comes to its
equilibrium distribution and then we
have to take a long time we have to
spend a long time drawing samples from
this equilibrium distribution and
averaging those samples in order to get
the estimate of the mean and so we
started to think about well what if
there are applications where we don't
need to take averages where we just want
to draw samples from the equilibrium
distribution because if that were the
case then we would probably we might be
able to get a much better speed up
because we wouldn't even have to do this
this long you know the longest or the
hardest part of our algorithm which is
moment estimation and so that I was
basically the Genesis of this um therm
oasian inference paper because we
started thinking like what kind of
problems is the output a sample from a
distribution what kind of problem you're
you don't want something that's a
deterministic function of the input but
you want a sample and one thing that
came uh that came up is sampling from
the basian posterior of some model so uh
so that's kind of a pretty common task
that that you know people want to do is
they have some parameter Theta say and
then some data observed data um y like
different samples y1 Y2 so on um and you
want to condition your you have some
prior distribution for your un your
hidden VAR or yeah you have some prior
distribution for your parameter Theta
and then you have a likelihood which is
like a theory of how the parameter Theta
determines the observed data Y and given
those two things you given your data and
your prior and your likelihood you want
to condition the the parameter Theta on
the data right um and then often you
want to sample from that um posterior
distribution the distribution that's
kind of been revised by the presence of
your data um and so we basically started
thinking about whether there's a way we
could use a similar approach based on a
physical
realization of like noisy uh lement
Dynamics in order to do beian inference
and and then wouldn't have to do moment
estimation or averaging and so we might
get much better speedups um and so
that's basically what we did in this
paper and I guess at a higher level
there's kind of a nice formalism for how
you can think about yeah just what what
is going on at a higher level and how
we're doing beian inference using a
physical system here um and so what it
is it's it's B it's related to the idea
of an energy-based model that one way of
parameterizing a probability
distribution p is to write that
probability distribution p is the
exponential of some energy function uh
so s or e to the minus E to the minus V
right so this just a way of of writing
so any distribution you can you can
write in this form but also importantly
this is the form a distribution will
take in statistical mechanics um when
you allow a system to come to
equilibrium and it has some energy V
this is the form of its kind of
equilibrium distribution um and so this
when you talk about probility
distributions in those terms it's often
called like an energy based model
approach um and there's something
convenient about using energy based
models for basian inference basically uh
which is that when you take the log of
your probability density function
instead of like multiplying together
probability density functions you end up
adding together energy functions because
we're now talking about the logs of the
probabilities instead of the
probabilities uh and so that's what's
going on with this equation here it says
you want to thet equal minus Ln of P
Theta minus Ln of py given Theta so here
um l p Theta is the prior that's our
Assumption of you know the distribution
for the parameters Theta before we've
gotten any measurements P of p y given
Theta is our Theory or model of how um
how y depends on Theta in other words
how does the data that we can observe
depend on the parameter that we that we
can't observe um and so what you would
do in in basis theorem is you know you
multiply together or you or not even
basis theorem just the the definition of
the joint distribution is p of theta and
Y is p of theta time P of Y given Theta
but now instead of multiplying these
things together we're going to be adding
them together because we're talking
about the energy um right so this energy
kind of represents the The Joint
distribution somehow because because it
includes the contributions from the
prior and the likelihood um and what so
what you do in these Thermo basan
inference problems is you start out with
one energy fun one potential energy uh
which can be thought of as like kind of
a a box that you know you could think of
the system as a as some well like in
thermodynamics we might think of it as
like a gas inside of a box and then you
can change the potential energy by
moving a piston in or out or something
like that or sometimes we think of it as
like a marble in a bowl and then you can
reshape the bowl um changing the
potential energy which is maybe closer
to like this picture here where when we
CH the potential energy we're like
changing the shape of this bowl
basically um so go back here what's
plotted in this uh panel a is what
happens when we vary when we change the
potential energy function over time so
between time zero and time one we're
going to change the potential energy
from a potential energy that's
associated with the prior uh to a which
is U so u0 equals minus log of P Theta
and and that's like this this blue curve
is the probability density when we're in
that prior distribution and then we
slowly change the potential or slowly or
quickly we change the potential energy
to U1 which is the distribution that
corresponds to the posterior basically
uh for for Theta um in other words it's
the distribution where you've
conditioned Theta on all of your all
your observed data basically uh and so
what we're seeing in this plot is that
as we as we change the poti over time
the distribution of the system changes
and it goes from this gaussian
distribution to this kind of asymmetric
distribution which in this case is the
posterior for like basian logistic
regression um and another view of that
is in panel B where we're looking at how
the thermodynamic quantities change over
time so whenever you're changing the
potential energy of a system the
potential energy function of a system
you can be doing work on the system uh
and so this orange curve here is beta
times work it's uh beta is one over KT
and we see that the potential energy
changes between time zero and time one
and during that window of time we're
doing work but then at time one the
potential energy stops changing and so
no no work is being done there um and so
we can see you know how how the you know
how much work is being done on the
system and then there's also heat um
which is the change in energy uh that's
not associated with the work being done
which you can compute just kind of using
the the first law that de equals DW
minus DQ um so we have work and heat
which are kind of the two most
fundamental thermodynamic quantities I
guess um and then we also have the free
energy also you know a quantity of great
importance and there's there's kind of
two different versions of free energy
that are that are plotted here so one is
this dashed line which is the
equilibrium free energy um and what that
means is that at each instant in time uh
the potential en is changing but we
could imagine a system that was in
equilibrium at that instant in time um
and if we did have a system that was in
equilibrium at that instant in time its
free energy would be the the the the
equilibrium free energy so that's kind
of the definition of equilibrium free
energy is the free energy of a system at
equilibrium with the instantaneous
potential um and then there's kind of
the non-equilibrium free energy uh which
can be which can basically be larger
than that um and the reason it can be
larger than that is that the system is
not in equilibrium at all times that if
you're quickly changing the potential
energy the system is driven out of
equilibrium and so you can kind of look
at the gap between these like the gap
between the dotted black line and the
solid black line as the extent to which
the system is out of equilibrium at each
moment in time and what happens is when
when we quickly change the potential
from Time Zero to time one the system is
coming out of equilibrium these these
two lines are getting farther apart and
then at time one we stop changing the
potential and the system starts to come
back into equilibrium basically um and
just another note on this is a nice
interpretation of the difference between
these um f minus F equilibrium is that
it's actually the KL Divergence or the
the call callback lior Divergence of
between the distribution of the system
at any time and the equilibrium
distribution uh so that's just another
way of saying that it characterizes how
to what extent the system is out of
equilibrium because this KL Divergence
is is basically a way of of quantifying
the distance it's not technically a a
distance measure but a kind of distance
between probability distributions and so
it turns out that this like f minus F
equilibrium is equal to the K Divergence
between the distribution and the
equilibrium distribution um so that's
kind of the general framework of like
what we're doing in thermo asan
inference is that we're we're setting up
a system so that we can change its
potential energy and we turn on we we
have a potential energy term that
represents the prior and we have another
kind of coupling term that represents
the likelihood and then we have like
physical degrees of freedom that
represent the observed data that we have
and when we turn on this interaction
between Theta and all these um
observational degrees of freedom then
you then the equilibrium distribution
Bec becomes the beian posterior and if
we wait for a long enough time then we
can measure the state data um and get
samples from the basian posterior uh so
let's see I I say a little bit more
about that um just in theory and how
that plays out but you might notice here
that this kind of is is the key to the
algorithm is this stochastic
differential equation here which is you
know similar to the form of the
stochastic differential equation I
showed on this slide equation
two um
and in that it has kind of this drift
term which is like the predictable
change in the state of the system and
then this um this noise term which is
like the unpredictable change in the
state um and so let's
see yeah I think that oh yeah okay so I
guess what I'll yeah I'll talk a little
bit about the examples we did in this
paper so we we we what we did was we
tried this out for two kinds of beian
inference like two examples a beijan
inference one of which is a gaussian
gussian model um so where you have a
gussian prior and a gaussian posterior
and the other is um basian logistic
regression so where you have like a
gussian prior and a logistic likelihood
um so so this plot here is for the
gaussian gaussian model um and we see
the um basically the prior is is one of
these you know Green ellipses and then
um the likelihood is you know the red
ellips or might be the other way around
but then you get the posterior which is
kind of in the middle somehow um and it
turns out that you can use this circuit
over here in order to sample from that
that blue ellipse uh that blue
distribution uh which we've actually
simulated this circuit in spice uh which
is you know popular Library popular
software package for simulating circuits
and so what you do is you you use one um
kind of you have one set of resistors
that's used to input the prior
covariance Matrix and another set of
resistors that's used to put in kind of
the likelihood uh Co covariance Matrix
and then once you do that you can
measure the currents like through these
inductors and measuring those currents
gives you a sample from the desired
posterior distribution um okay so yeah I
guess that's at a high level what I
wanted to say about this Gan gussian
model case were there any questions
about either the overview like the
general picture of therm Asian inference
or about like this gaussian gussian
model yeah a few questions how do you
know that you aren't too confident or
not confident enough with respect to the
posterior like your Precision or your
attention what makes you not just H how
do you get confidence in your confidence
level MH such that you can draw a a
useful basy incredible interval rather
than for example making it much wider or
much tighter I see right like how in
other words like how do we test that
we're actually drawing from the right
posterior kind of yeah if you can can
compare it with the exact compute then
you've already done that computation so
then when do you feel like it's okay to
get out without the guide rails and take
the thermodynamic estimate as it is
without doing secondary
calibrations yeah so that's a good
question right so one of the nice things
about the gaussian gaussian model is it
is one of these very few cases where
there is an analytical solution so you
can compute exactly what the posterior
like the posterior is a gaussian again
and you can compute exactly what the
mean and covariance Matrix of that Gan
are and so we can compare them um but I
think you're also alluding to the fact
that you know eventually we we aren't
going to have that guard rail and we're
just going to say we're now confident
enough that this system can example from
the true posterior and we're kind of
done with with testing it and yeah I
think the question of like when exactly
do we become confident enough that it it
gets the right posterior is maybe not
completely solved yet um but I would say
that because in the gaussian gussian
case there's an analytical solution I
feel pretty confident that like we can
do enough testing even at pretty high
Dimensions that we'll be able to you
know assure ourselves basically that it
works but where that becomes more
difficult is for cases where there is no
analytical solution to compare to um
like uh in the case of the basan
logistic regression which we also do
here and in that case the best thing you
can do is just kind of run a Monte Carlo
simulation digitally and compare that to
the results that we would predict with
spice or compared to experimental
results um which also works is just much
much more expensive computationally um
but on the other hand the fact that it's
much more expensive computationally
means that there's that we're solving a
really hard problem uh which is good but
yeah I guess yeah the to to make a long
story short um that's still kind of
something we're g to have to figure out
you know in in complete detail is like
how do we do enough tests and what tests
we have to do to assure ourselves that
that it gets to the right posterior yeah
another interesting piece was
that changing differential between the
equilibrium free energy
and the the non-equilibrium
so do you experiment with like different
speeds and find a tradeoff between
moving it too fast but taking you too
far out of equilibrium but then is there
any downside to just moving it super
fast or do you uh get better accuracy
your performance in the kind of infant
asmal movement case keeping it close to
equilibrium all along the way
way right so that's a that's a really
good question and actually something
that we're probably that that's a focus
like a current kind of research focus is
like what is the like given that we have
this freedom of like how quickly we want
to turn on the potential how quickly we
want to turn on the interactions um what
should we do with that freedom basically
uh and there's like this really
interesting literature on like energy
time tradeoffs in stochastic Thermo so
let me see if real quick I can pull up
this paper um werstein
uh
um well just while you're looking for it
you mentioned probably approximately
correct that's Lesly Valiant that's
right Lesly Valiant that's right exactly
yeah um thanks
um yeah so okay so I can't find exactly
the reference I'm looking for but
basically what it says is that one so I
talked about the KL Divergence which is
one way of quantifying the difference
between two probability distributions
another way of quantifying the
difference between two distributions is
the the werstein distance which um is
kind of has this very deep and elegant
theory in in kind of optimal transport
uh Theory and where was sign distance
came from originally was was optimal
transport problems and in particular how
do I transform one configuration of some
material say into another configuration
or if I have like a mound of dirt and I
want to move the mound of dirt and also
reshape it uh how how many shovels full
of dirt am I going to have to take
basically and that's kind of the
classical um canich problem uh or
there's there's another guy who well I
think it's it's the other guy the
problem I'm thinking of but they're
they're these two dual optimal transport
problems that are basically the same
thing that are that problem of
transforming one mound of dirt into
another and the washer sign distance is
the amount of shovels of dirt you need
basically to carry to transform one
distribution into another um so you can
think of it as like accounting for it
accounts for like not just um assigning
low probability to high probability
events with one distribution versus the
other but also like if the mean of one
distribution is very different than the
other then you can think of it as like
having to move a lot of Mass from one
place to another and the kind of cool
result that there is in in statistical
mechanics and in particular like
stochastic ther
around this waserstein distance is that
if you want to change a system State um
over time then there's like this
tradeoff you need to pay between the
amount of work that you dissipate and
the amount of time that you take and it
ends up the form of that trade-off is
that the product of the dissipated work
and the time duration of your protocol
is lower bounded by uh something times
the waserstein distance um so I guess
you can think of that as like given that
I have two distributions that are a
certain distance away from each other I
can either transform from one to the
other really quickly but dissipating a
lot of work in other words paying a lot
of energy or I can do it really slowly
without paying really any work at all or
I can take some trade-off do something
in between where I kind of slowly CH
change from one to the other and spend a
medium amount of work and what we're
interested in doing is applying these
you know this formulation this theory of
waserstein distance and trade-off
between energy and time to solving
problems like this one like doing basian
inference and kind of saying there's
like this optimal Frontier of there's
not just one optimal solution uh because
you might be in a situation where you
care more about speed than you care
about energy or you might be in a
situation where you care more about
energy than about speed but there is a
set of solutions that are optimal with
respect to kind of your disposition
towards and how you value energy and
time and I think it's basically related
to these like energy time trade-offs
that's kind of a classic pure SL metab
basing approach anytime you have a free
parameter treat that as another kind of
variable to do inference on um what is
the work Reservoir as we're not exactly
picking up weights and lifting them to a
higher elevation or anything so the heat
Reservoir makes sense in terms of
standard thermodynamics heat bath and
all that but what's happening with the
work Reservoir and what is it touching
or doing with the
device yeah yeah that's a great great
question too so if I go back to um to
this picture for a second here you can
you can visualize these systems again
it's like a collection of masses coupled
together on Springs and then what we're
doing when we're changing the potential
energy is we're like changing the spring
constants of some of these Springs so
like maybe each of these Springs has
like a little screw on it that you can
turn with a screw driver to make it like
more or less stretchy basically um but
you need to like draw a boundary between
the system and what's outside the system
somewhere and where we draw that
boundary is that what whatever is
turning that screw that's tightening you
know that that's changing the spring
constant is not part of our system and
so that if if you need to do work if it
costs energy in in order to turn the
screw then that needs to come from
somewhere and we're calling that a work
Reservoir and so we might actually be
like lifting weights up and down if
those if that's where the energy comes
from in order to change the parameters
of the potential energy function we're
just kind of saying that wherever that
energy comes from if we have some
battery or some you know flywheel or
whatever that's kind of outside of our
system and we're not really going to not
really going to worry about it Beyond
just quantifying how much energy it uh
it uh interchanges with the system
basically yeah yeah it's it's
interesting that the device almost has
these dual reservoirs it's it's like one
of those toothpastes with a dividing
line in the middle and squirting out
both kinds because on one hand it's
interfacing with heat defined as that
which does not do work just the thermal
dissipative and then on the other hand
it's connected into the work
Reservoir which is sort of the
complement of heat M and then the device
is is interfacing with both of them and
as you described seeking to find a path
or a trajectory for
itself that isn't leave that's not
either dissipating extra heat
unnecessarily or
leaving work convertible work on the
table either because it's sort of able
to interface or or mediate between the
work and the heat
here right yeah yeah and there's a
really a nice interpretation of that too
I think um I I the the way you put it as
like a a toothpaste tube where it can
come in one in and out the other or
something like that um and it is it's
it's well you see a lot of diagrams like
this where you have a heat you know you
have you're interchanging both heat and
work with an environment in the context
of like heat engines right because you
have a heat engine that well often there
will be three W reservoirs in that case
like you'll take in heat from a hot
Reservoir dump out heat to a cold
Reservoir and then do work or something
but here we have two things we have just
have a heat Reservoir and a work
Reservoir but there is a way of thinking
about this as a kind of heat engine like
thing um but it's it's more of a
refrigerator than a heat engine I guess
because the the goal of a heat engine is
to take heat and then output work of
course you also have to Output heat
somewhere but that's that's the goal is
to use heat as a resource in order to
Output work but what we want to do here
is we're actually going to input work
and then we're going to Output heat and
as a result the entropy of our system
decreases uh and this is just kind of a
general thing that happens when you
condition one random variable on another
the entropy on average uh of the
variable you conditioned decreases
because the mutual information has to be
positive so this is just one of these
fundamental like information Theory
things because of the positivity of the
mutual information conditioning on a
random variable decrease the entropy and
you can think of in in some sense like
decreasing the entropy of your system as
as the operation of a refrigerator um
even though it's not necessarily
decreasing the temperature per se but it
is decreasing the entropy um and so
there's kind of yeah this nice way of
looking at this as like a heat engine
but really a refrigerator where you have
this flow of work in and heat out and
and decrease in the entropy basically
but but just one quick not on that of
course you can't decrease the entropy of
the whole universe so the entropy has to
be increased somewhere to compensate for
that and that's what's happening where
we have heat flowing out into the heat
Reservoir so the entropy of the heat
Reservoir is increasing to compensate
could you maybe give a little detail how
do real empirical measures y1 Y2 Etc
come in like in active inference we're
often thinking about perception as
inference or action selection as
inference but just on on the perception
side so some perceptual prior new
observation comes in new Photon hits the
retina or whatever it may be new new
thermometer reading comes in for the iot
and H how does that feed into this and
and how do you how do you schedule or
bring that empirical measurement
in right yeah so we think of the the
measured data these observations y1 Y2
YN as representing constraints on the
system somehow and so when you when you
get new data you introduce kind of
another one of these constraints by
writing down your observation and then
coupling that those phys and then those
physical degrees of freedom that store
the observation then get coupled to your
system uh subsystem Theta but like just
to make it kind of concrete of like yeah
how does that actually happen so in this
circuit here the the degrees of freedom
that represent Theta are the currents
going through these inductors L1 and L2
and the um degrees of freedom that
represent an observe data point why are
the currents that are provided by these
current sources um i1 Prime and I2 Prime
and so what you do when you get data is
you turn on these current sources and
set their current the current that
they're programmed output as equal to
the um the components of the data that
you got um but you could also maybe
something you said actually I thought
was really interesting which was in
terms of like thinking about observation
as like perception or learning from
perception um and you maybe could even
think of these maybe if we got rid of
these current sources and just had the
environment kind of coupled these wires
and somehow it's like taking a
measurement of the environment directly
more or less and then conditioning on
those I think that that's also like kind
of a valid interpretation which hadn't
really I hadn't really thought of before
but I think that's an interesting way to
think about this as being kind of having
these perception inputs here that are
coupled to the environment and then
conditioning its internal state based on
those
somehow cool yeah I mean a
neurological analogy to these circuits
are like there's some neural manifold
and spiking patterns or neural
electrical fields are traversing and
they they're they're itinerating around
this manifold describing the
pre-observation state then a new
observation comes in if it's not
attended to it's like an uncoupled
aesome later like the observation that
isn't attended to it's as if it didn't
happen tree falling in the forest and
all that whereas if it the observation
is strongly attended to and there's a
strong coupling between the observation
and the resonating state of the the
prior then it moves more to be
influenced by that observation more
strongly and then hierarchical systems
just have series of layers
with possibly different attentions to
layers with with
resonating uh information coming from
the environment in towards the deeper
priors like of the organism and then and
then more on the outbound action
selection is when it opens up to well
maybe the uh prior from the higher
levels Cascades out and gets reflected
as action modifying the environment to
be more like the priors of the organism
that's the change the world direction of
active
inference ongoing with the change your
mind Direction updating the priors to be
more aligned with what the environment
is
giving I see yeah I think that's a
really cool way of of looking at of
looking at this um in in that like yeah
exactly as you said that like if you're
not uh if there's no coupling between
the degrees of freedom representing the
parameters you're estimating if if if
those are coupled to some source of
information in the environment then yeah
it's like you're paying attention to it
in some way whereas if there's no
coupling it's yeah it's it's for the
purpose of your of your beian inference
it didn't happen or or the information
just isn't there and so somehow like the
con conditioning on a piece of
information is represented is like
embodied physically as a physical
coupling between kind of your we your
description of the the ween variable and
the actual physical encoding of of The
observed data I think um and and then
the other thing yeah the other piece you
mentioned about like what about kind of
some feedback effect where like you as
as a result of your knowledge of this
variable you come up with some policy
for like how to behave or something like
that and then that will actually change
maybe that will have an influence on the
next observations you get and that's a
really interesting direction as well I
think like for the purpose of this paper
we've just assumed like all the
observations are independent of each
other uh and and that would kind of
break down if you assume that like if
you were using um some kind of uh
decision you know decision strategy or
policy to make decisions based on the
data you get and your estimate of the
state your estimate of the parameters
data to inform your your future
decisions in like maybe like a
reinforcement learning setup um but
definitely like figuring out how to use
this Hardware in that context is
something of of interest you know of
current interest for us now so I I'll
definitely you know keep keep people
posted as as that progresses for sure
yeah cool feel free to keep going if
there's any other pieces you want to
explore and then people watching live
can write any questions in the chat uhuh
cool okay um so I think that yeah so one
thing I haven't talked about yet with
this paper is our results on complexity
uh which is of course is a really
important part of it because that's what
motivates Us in the end is like why we
go to this effort of build this totally
new kind of device in order to solve
problems we already have a way to solve
them um but it's just really hard it's
you know intractable a lot of the time
the sample from basian posteriors if you
have to run some very long uh you know
Markov processor or you know some Monte
Carlo simulation uh so we have some
results um oh yeah and I also kind of
hinted at this earlier that we expected
that we might get better speedups in
this case than in the case of the TLA
the thermo and your algebra algorithms
because in this case we don't have to do
moment estimation just want to Output
samples um and so that did kind of turn
out to be true that we got pretty
significant like predicted speed UPS
so just for this case of the gaussian
gaussian model where we're given like a
gaussian prior and a gaussian likelihood
and some data and then we want a sample
from the gaussian posterior we found
that the amount of time that it takes
that the amount of time you have to wait
between when you in when you input your
uh when you input the problem and when
you output the samples scales
logarithmically with the size of the
matrices involved basically um which is
pretty good time scaling because if you
think about like what you would have to
do digitally to accomplish this You'
have to like get the inverse of a matrix
you have to get the inverses of two
matrices and like add those together and
take an inverse again that's essentially
the process you need to do when you want
to do conditioning for gaussians um and
so that's something that would basically
be n cubed time maybe you know somewhere
between n s and n cubed uh using
state-of-the-art algorithms and so if we
can do that in the amount of time that
scales with log n that sounds really
good um it almost sounds too good to be
true in a way because you know how is it
that we went from polinomial to
logarithmic it almost sounds like an
exponential speed up and it's I think
like I while I think that these this
result is really cool I don't it's not
quite that cool in that it's it's not
like fundamentally changing a polinomial
operation to a a logarithmic and the
reason is because we also have to look
at the energy cost um and when you look
at the amount of energy that go the the
energy consumed by the algorithm
basically scales linearly with the size
of the problem so we get this scaling
where we have um logarithmic time in
dimension and linear energy in dimension
which is still like a pretty significant
uh Improvement um and
then we also did some analysis of the
like time complexity for the um basian
uh logistic regression uh scenario and
we found there we were able to show that
you also get like um logarithmic uh
scaling with Dimension but we weren't we
haven't yet figured out the like energy
scaling analysis for the logistic
progression because that circuit ended
up being a bit more complicated and it
uses these like differential pairs of
transistors to get kind of logistic
functions um and it's a little bit uh
involved to like try to estimate all the
energy um but those were the the two
kind of circuits we we gave in the paper
was this one for doing the gaussian
gaussian model and this one for doing
the um basian logistic progression and
we have some promising results on like
the time and energy complexity of those
operations um so oh I guess and one
other just kind of interesting note
about the interpretation and that also
informs like how we derive these scaling
results is that there's kind of this
interesting literature on like
waserstein gradient flows um which is uh
basically
you can think of like when when the
probability distribution is changing
over time here you can think of that
probability distribution as a vector in
like a very high dimensional space or
really an infinite dimensional space and
the Dynamics of that Vector can be
thought of as actually a gradient
descent on some objective function uh
and it turns out that what that
objective function is is actually that
callback lior Divergence or the
difference in free energy between you
know F and feq and then it's and then
the distance that um kind of the step
size of that gradient descent is
measured in terms of the washer Stein
distance which is that distance between
distributions I talked about earlier so
you can think of this is um like the
Dynamics of the probability distribution
as like an ordinary differential
equation in an infinite dimensional
space where it's like going in the line
of gradient of steepest Ascent in K
Divergence with respect to changes in
was time distance um but yeah those were
the main things I wanted to talk about
in this paper I guess and maybe yeah at
this point we can see if there's any uh
questions from the audience or
something cool yeah I think people will
definitely be interested in that
connection with free energy where the
kale Divergence comes up in both the
variational free energy bounding the
basy and surprise and expected free
energy which is when considering policy
inference as computation as a cognitive
process and looking over expected
observations asking what SE what policy
dependent sequence of expected
observations would have what epistemic
and pragmatic value so these circuits
aren't planning they're in the
variational free energy kind of mode but
it's interesting that again we see K
Divergence popping up in both and and
different divergences and distances
between
distributions being basically the Crux
of the question and which
measurements about which distributional
distances and which properties of
distributional distances and
divergences can be
enacted or how costly is it to emulate
them when those are the calculations
that it's important to know and the most
classic of all being basically prior
going to
posterior how much should
update right yeah yeah I really like
yeah what you were just saying because I
I think yeah I'm kind of aware of of
these I've read I heard a little bit
about um like kind of these
interpretations of K Divergence as like
in terms of games and like how how much
do you expect to kind of lose or win if
you have some assumption about the
distribution of a parameter that if if
kind of your distribution for a
parameter isn't the actual distribution
or something like that and how how well
or badly do you do this game based on
your kind of estimate of a distribution
um and I think that I really like that
that characterization of it because it
gets it kind of a more like endtoend
measure of quality uh because if you
yeah if you if you use some system to
accelerate the computations you need to
power an agent and then you want to
estimate like quantify how good is your
system really doing then what people
will care more about at the end of the
day isn't necessarily like what's the uh
like you know what's the relative error
between these two matrices or vectors
but more like what how much uh you know
how how um how often will I make the
right decision or something like that
basically or what's my expected reward
based on decisions I make and so I think
that yeah if we can if we can somehow
introduce the kale Divergence in in on
that end as well that'll be a really
nice way to kind of formulate
things how do you see these elements
playing a role in systems engineering
and design like is it something that
gets brought in like another kind of GPU
or
CPU we've talked about processing but
not really about memory or storage so
how do you see this playing a role in
whether specialized inference pipelines
or consumer Hardware or what right yeah
that's a that's a great question I think
there's really two ways to look at it
one is like what what how do the
theoretical results matter in terms of
the future of computing Hardware um and
I think that like these theoretical
results can be pretty influential like
thing like scaling laws like you know
like like um Moors law and stuff like
that or like how Land hours principle
informs how people think about what's
the minimum amount of energy that you
can achieve with a computation and I
think that there's one like impact of
you know these theoretical results is
that it kind of gives you a a bar to aim
for and that if we can say like this is
the energy time tradeoff for be and
inference you can you can do it this
fast if you pay this much energy but if
you go a little bit slower then you can
save some energy then that kind of sets
The Benchmark for like what people
should hope to achieve with new hardware
whether or not they're using our uh
Paradigm but and then there's the other
kind of way of looking at it which is
just a more kind of literal level is
like what's the path from these designs
we've presented in this paper to
actually building hardware and where
will that Hardware go and what will it
do so I guess the exciting news kind of
on that front is that yeah we talked a
little bit about on on Twitter recently
how we got funding from an an agency in
the UK called Arya that's like their new
more or less their version of DARPA kind
of that they recently created um and is
is really interested in bringing down
the costs of AI like in terms of the
hardware production cost and also like
the energy and time cost of training um
and even and inference as well um and so
they've kind of funded our our project
on a timeline of you know let's say like
we're we're aiming to have Hardware in
the next you know three four five years
basically uh at kind of varying level of
of um kind of increasing the dimension
that it'll increasing the size of the
problems it'll be able to solve um but
in terms of yeah like where exactly that
Hardware will go or who will Who will
end up using it I think that there's
still like there's still some open
questions around that um and and more
like I'm more working on yeah the side
of like designing the algorithms and
trying to figure out
what you know what error mitigation or
erir correction techniques we can come
up with to make it work better and make
it more robust but yeah I hopefully you
know yeah maybe next time you know I
I'll have more a more detailed answer on
that but I think yeah at the moment
there's it's not totally set in stone
yeah what else do you think is out there
in terms of land
hour you know what what bounds are you
scraping up against or what big powder s
of information and work and heat do you
think might be out there and and touched
upon by this line of
inquiry right so I guess like one kind
of historical note is that like for a
long time people have focused a lot on
on just kind of land hour's Principle as
like the fundamental Bound for computing
um and and just for you know the
audience and people who aren't
necessarily familiar what land hour
principle says is that to erase a bit of
information
you need to dissipate an amount of heat
uh which is log 2times um KT so in other
words if you can run your computer at a
very low temperature then you don't have
to dissipate as much information but
there's still you know amount of of work
that sorry did dis paay heat there's
still amount of um energy that you have
to pay that's proportional to the amount
of Aer that you have to do now the issue
with Land hours principle one issue is
that it's something that we haven't
really been able to achieve um there's
nice kind of plot on one of these slides
about it like showing how well we are
still getting you know more and more
efficiency that we're still well Above
This thermodynamic Li limit which is
Land hours Bound in terms of how much
energy we we pay um and so I think the
trend more recently is to say well we
need to also account for time because
land hour principle doesn't really
account for time it you know assumes you
can do what you're doing like infinitely
slow and in reality you know we don't
want to do computations infinitely
slowly and so that's kind of yeah the
angle I'm thinking
about when I'm I'm saying like let's try
using these um kind of uh these results
from stochastic Thermo that bound like
energy the product of energy in time
using the washer sign distance but I
think that like I've just kind of dipped
you know a finger into that literature
and there's a lot of work on on that
stuff in ter in like speed limits uh
especially in like Quantum systems
Quantum speed limits and and classical
speed limits and so yeah that that's
like I guess the line the pattern I'm
I'm most excited about is using these
bound on like the product of energy and
time in terms of you know distance
measures between distributions but there
may be you know may be other patterns as
well so definitely curious to hear yeah
if any other ideas I think come to mind
but
yeah yeah that's exciting to bring time
into the equation literally and and for
for real embodied systems that have
existence in space and
time that their material properties and
the
propagation maybe even coming down to um
speed of sound speed of light deoration
velocities and and these sorts of things
could become dominant in terms of
whether um the bulldozzer moves a few
large amounts of Earth with great cost
or whether it's very fine grains of sand
MH which might be very efficient but
then it might take so long that for for
a practical situation it doesn't
really have
utility yeah yeah absolutely and and I
think like one the one reason I'm I'm
really excited about yeah as you put it
like bring time into the equation is
kind of at a higher level like big
picture I think that where things are
going in terms of the theory is like
some kind of unification between like
computational complexity Theory and
stochastic Thermo because like we've
we've been approaching some of the same
problems with of of like yeah how
fundamentally does your resource costs
of like energy and time scale with the
size of a system uh kind of as it scales
um but so far like we we haven't like I
think fully broken through to see the
shape that connection takes and and yeah
the approach that I'm that I kind of
take to that is like first go for the
low hanging fruit like not you know
we're not necessarily going to see it
all at once like what is this
relationship between stochastic Thermo
and complexity Theory but the more we
can like build up these little results
of like well you can um by looking by
building constructing kind of a
thermodynamic system that you're going
to change the parameters do work on and
see it as this kind of heat engine or
refrigerator you can achieve a certain
computational complexity of this
operation I think these like smaller
results are are helping to you know
bring bring the those two Fields a
little closer together maybe yeah
interesting also with time it's almost
like it's like with a body there's a
baseline a basil metabolic rate and then
exercise is doing extra activity on top
of that so it's like if you have to pay
the upkeep on the energy of the circuit
even if it only is using a little bit of
extra activity to do the target
computation you're still paying for a
large block of time the Baseline
level and so when we get to the thermal
limit then the Baseline is
free because it's happening at a
temperature that's it's it's happening
at an ambient temperature so it's not
needing to be powered to give some of
the sampling Dynamics in the same way
the the the informative sampling and
that's the part that that I think
there's still so much learning and and
interest in how how do these higher
moments arise with with no extra work
that seems like good
information and yet it's falling out of
what seems to be powered just from
thermal
vibration yeah know I I definitely like
think about it in those terms as in like
what are the sources like fundamentally
the sources of energy
we have energy takes the form of work or
heat and and heat is like cheap and work
is expensive right because heat just
kind of comes from a reservoir can come
from anywhere and it's not organized and
yeah in work you have to you have to go
to some trouble to actually get a a
source of work so yeah I definitely
think about like that like how can we
optimize a computation so that more of
the energy comes from heat as opposed to
work basically but
yeah yes I think that's that's exactly
it having having something rather than
needing to add energy from the wall so
that the energy gets pushed through a
system does some computation and
dissipates the extras heat it's almost
like there's another Avenue where the
heat in the
room vibrates the system to functionally
implement that computation or cognitive
process
it's it's all about
arbitraging heat and work in new ways
and seeing basian updating and
equilibrium and far from equilibrium
processes as happening as sort of a
first principle of intelligent
matter yeah yeah yeah I think that's
really cool really cool way to see it
actually yeah absolutely um yeah and and
I guess yeah one one other thing I'll
say I guess that I was thinking is um in
terms of yeah like like how where where
do we look for kind of fundamental
constraints on computation in terms of
the resource costs I think that a lot of
people some some people have taken the
view that like really land the land
hours principle is kind of what what's
the most is the most fundamental thing
and then the reason we aren't achieving
it is just kind of practical
considerations on some level is just
that it's hard to engineer but yeah my
Outlook is is more that like well maybe
there's a fundamental reason that it is
hard to engineer something you know
maybe there's a fundamental tradeoff
that we just haven't discovered yet that
if we knew about would actually very
well explain why we're still a thousand
or three or four orders of magnitude
above Land hours principle so yeah I'm
hoping that it's that maybe just
considering time will get us there if
not then yeah there's there's more to
think about but yeah who who knows I
guess at this point but
yeah cool do you have any final riddles
or thoughts or
comments um yeah I can't think of
anything else yeah I think this is I
think I really covered everything that
yeah I was hoping to get across I I
think so far it's been really good it's
been really great um but uh yeah if
there was any any questions from the
audience we of course be happy to take
those yeah okay no specific questions
this was very informative Max I think
it's it's
uh been a topic coming up again and
again with these not just similarities
and differences and analogies but
implementations
of information
geometries and
information processes on
embodiment on physical embodiment
biological designed and and all of this
and so it certainly feels like there's a
lot of threads swimming around and and
exciting opportunities for synthesis so
thank you for this exciting research and
and the empirical connections and
everything absolutely thanks for having
me um and yeah as I as I mentioned
earlier like when we first started out
on This research we definitely had no
idea or or didn't anticipate at all that
it would lead us to kind of these these
things that can be interpreted in terms
of like active inference and connections
to that um and and like free energy but
uh yeah it's just been really exciting
for me that to yeah be working on
something I think is is both a practical
approach to improving our landscape of
hardware for AI but also has these
interesting deep you know thermodynamic
interpretations so yeah definitely I'm
I'm happy to come back anytime and chat
more I thought this was really really
fun cool let's check back in a couple
months in a couple in a couple trillion
oscillations of the cesium as they
say all right thank you Max fawell yeah
you bye have a good
one e